A Inventory of the German Pictorial Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
German Pictorial Collection
1890-1999
XX766
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 8 slide boxes, 44 envelopes, 1 oversize folder (2.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs, postcards, and slides, depicting various political, military, and naval scenes in Germany, including communist rallies in the 1920s, the Berlin blockade of 1948-1949, and various prominent German personalities, including East German head of state Walter Ulbricht.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Ulbricht, Walter, 1893-1973--Pictorial works.; Communism--Germany--Pictorial works.; Berlin (Germany)--History--Blockade, 1948-1949--Pictorial works.; Germany--Pictorial works.
Container List
- 1 print of Count Helmuth K. B. von Moltke, 1890 (File A)
- 3 prints of the Royal Bavarian Army during its return to Munich, December 1918; 6 prints of a Stahlhelm parade in Berlin with Prince August Wilhelm and other Stahlhelm leaders reviewing it, ca. 1927. (File B)
- 46 prints and postcards depicting Communist rallies and parades in Germany, held under the auspices of the Roter Frontkaempferbund and other organizations, 1922-1929. (File C)
- 197 negatives and 2 strips of uncut film depicting units of the German Navy during the period 1937-1938, including scenes of the launchings of the battle cruiser Prinz Eugen, and the aircraft carrier Graf Zeppelin; visits by foreign naval vessels and their crews, and general scenes of life on board ship. (File D-E)
- 1 print of Paul von Hindenburg, with his signature. (File mF)
- 1 print of Paul von Hindenburg. (File m*G)
- 1 print of Adolf Hitler. (File mH)
- 5 prints of Adolf Hitler, ca. 1936-1940 (File m*G)
  including a scene at Obersalzberg, and with Hermann Goering.
- 1 print of Hermann Goering. (File mI)
- 1 print of Hermann Goering, ca. 1940 (File m*G)
- 1 print of Joseph Goebbels (File m*G)
- 2 prints (and 2 negatives) of heinrich Himmler (File J)
- 1 print (and 1 negative) of Field-Marshal Erwin Rommel. (File K)
- 6 prints of a storm trooper trophy. Part of the inscription reads: "Reichsinnungsmeister Pokal der S.A. gestiftet vom Deutschen Schuhmacherhandwerk" (File L)
- 11 prints of eleven leading Nazis convicted at the Nuremberg trial of major German war criminals, 1945-1946, taken immediately after their execution. (File M)
- 124 prints and 8 negatives of scenes in Berlin during the blockade of 1948-1949. (File mN-mY)
  Captions in mN.
- 24 prints of the city of Reutlingen, Germany, and vicinity, 1951. (File Z)
- 1 print of German politician Erich Ollenhauer, (1901-1963). (File AA)
- 41 prints depicting events in the life of Walter Ulbricht while growing up and during his rise to power, ca. 1893-1961. (File AB)
- 20 prints depicting events in the life of Walter Ulbricht as leader of East Germany, late 1950's and early 1960's. (File AC)
  Captions included in envelopes.
- 1 postcard of Karl Kautsky (File AD)
- 50 prints depicting military activities of the German Army, 1935-1940. (File AE)
- 1 small album containing 15 interior shots of Hitler's country house on the Obersalzberg. (File AF)
- 14 slides of an unidentified strongman/performer; 14 slides of groups of unidentified German officers, c.1920; 11 slides of an unidentified theater production; 12 slides of the Seemannschule Arcona near Berlin, 1930; 8 slides of members of the communist Roter Frontkampferbund; 4 slides depicting Reichsleiter der NSDAP, Robert Ley, addressing a rally of the Nationalsozilaistische Betriebsorganisation. (Box 1)
- 98 slides depicting theater productions, ship launchings, and other miscellaneous activities. (Box 1-2)
- 66 posters depicting youth and education in the German Democratic Republic. (Box 3)
- 80 slides, 1981-1987, depicting East and West Berlin; and 2 slides depicting the fall of the Berlin Wall, December 1989. (Box 4-8)
- 33 slides of the Berlin Wall, and of troops, tanks and other scenes in Berlin (Box 9)
- 2 prints of the Berlin Wall depicting the flight of an East German soldier in 1961 and the destruction of the Reconciliation Church in 1985. (File AG)
- 11 prints depicting the Berlin Wall on December 31, 1989. (File AH)
- 3 prints of East Berlin, 1989 December and 4 prints of the Berlin Wall, 1986-1987. (File AI)
- 31 slides depicting campaign posters for the 1990 October 14 elections in East Germany (File AJ)
- 9 prints depicting propaganda posters inside an East German cigarette factory in Dresden and 1 print of a Dresden street. (File AK)
- 71 prints depicting Berlin (East and West) in November 1989. (File AL)
  Includes 7 prints of the Berlin Wall and 2 prints of the Brandenburg Gate.
- 8 prints depicting campaign posters for the 1990 March 18 elections in East Germany. (File AM)
- 23 prints depicting slabs of the Berlin Wall. (File AN)
- 14 prints depicting Berlin (East and West), 1990. (File AO)
  Includes 12 prints of the Berlin Wall.
- 16 postcards, 1992, depicting political graffiti and wall painting, scenes of daily life, and historical sites in Berlin. (File AP)
- 1 print of Angela Hammitsch, sister of Adolf Hitler, 1945; 10 prints of Berlin, ca. 1945-1949; and 10 prints Konrad Adenauer, Helmut Schmidt, and other West German politicians (File AQ)
- 5 color photographs of neo-Nazi graffiti in Berlin, ca. 1991-1994. (File AR)
- 3 color photographs of the Reichstag, Berlin, n.d. (File AS)
- Photograph of the Reichstag, Berlin, 1999. 2 photographs of the Bundestag (Box 10)